## Stuart William David Grieve

Postdoctoral Research Associate

University of Edinburgh School of GeoSciences Drummond Street Edinburgh, EH8 9XP United Kingdom **८** +44 (0)7812 729 542 **S.grieve@ed.ac.uk** 

**O** sgrieve

**Blog**: sgrieve.github.io/

Google Scholar: Stuart W D Grieve

## **Appointments**

2016- **Postdoctoral Research Associate**, University of Edinburgh

Topographic analysis and landslide modelling software.

2016 Research Assistant, Cardiff University

### Education

2013–2016 Ph.D. in Atmospheric and Environmental Sciences University of Edinburgh

*Uncovering signatures of geomorphic process through high resolution topography.*Supervisors: Professor Simon M Mudd and Dr Tristram C Hales (Cardiff University)

2011–2012 M.Sc. in Geographical Information Science (Distinction) University of Edinburgh

Thesis Title: An automated analysis of the southern San Andreas Fault to explore topography's relationship with tectonics.

Supervisor: Professor Simon M Mudd

**B.Sc.** (Hons.) in Geology and Physical Geography (2:1) University of Edinburgh

Thesis Title: The Influence of Climate Change on Landslide Sediment Yields in the Northern

Lake District.

2007-2011

### Research Statement

My research aims to develop an understanding of how sediment transport processes are reflected in landscape morphology, and in particular how sediment is transported from hill-slopes into channels. The mechanisms of this transport range from the motion of individual particles through to large scale slope failures and debris flows. In particular, I aim to bridge the gap between models and reality and identify topographic signatures of local scale sediment transport processes, which converge to shape landforms at scales beyond their initial region of influence. I am also working to link forest growth models to shallow landslide hazard, to better understand slope stability in locations where forests are rapidly changing, in many cases due to human impacts.

I conduct such research through the development of open source software which facilitates reproducible topographic analysis, with a particular focus on the processing of high resolution topographic data. Such software allows repeatable experiments to be performed on both terrestrial and Martian landscapes, at a range of scales spanning individual hillslopes to continental scale features. I am also interested in the application of cutting edge GIS and computer science techniques to enhance surface process research, through the analysis of complex spatial information combined with novel data collection approaches.

## **Teaching Statement**

My teaching, as with my research, focuses on the implementation and application of quantitative and computational methods, as a framework to understand Earth surface processes. I am passionate about engaging students to interpret landscapes and the processes which act upon them both in a classroom and field setting. I have experience of teaching theoretical and applied GIS, either within the context of physical geography or a number of other disciplines (transport planning, infrastructure, crime research, archaeology) at both an undergraduate and postgraduate level. Aside from teaching physical geography and GIS, I also enjoy teaching scientific programming to students, giving them a grounding in data analysis and visualisation which can be employed throughout their time in education and beyond. Such skills are vital for students and I believe I am well placed to teach these skills within a physical science context.

#### **Technical Skills**

Accomplished programmer comfortable with object orientated concepts and a range of languages (C++, Python, Java, Visual Basic, Perl) and the use of version control (git, subversion) to manage large projects. Extensive experience in desktop (ArcGIS, FME, Whitebox, QGIS) and web based (MapBox, Mapguide) GIS to solve complex spatial problems. Managing large spatial and non-spatial datasets using SQL databases (Oracle, PostgreSQL, MySQL, SQLite). Processing raw LiDAR point clouds to produce bare earth DEMs.

# Other Employment

2015–2016 2012–2013 **GIS Consultant and Field Course Leader**, GeoBus, University of St Andrews **GIS Trainee** Forth Crossing Bridge Constructors

#### **Publications**

- Grieve, S.W.D., Mudd, S.M., Hurst, M.D., *How long is a hillslope?* Earth Surf. Process. Landforms. doi:10.1002/esp.3884
- Grieve, S.W.D., Mudd, S.M., Hurst, M.D., Milodowski, D.T., *A nondimensional framework for exploring the relief structure of landscapes*. Earth Surf. Dynam., doi:10.5194/esurf-4-309-2016
- Grieve, S.W.D., Mudd, S.M., Milodowski, D.T., Clubb, F.J., Furbish, D.J., *How does grid-resolution modulate the topographic expression of geomorphic processes?* Earth Surf. Dynam., doi:10.5194/esurf-4-627-2016
- Parker, R.N., Hales, T.C., Mudd, S.M., **Grieve, S.W.D.**, Constantine, J.A., *Colluvium supply in humid regions limits the frequency of storm-triggered landslides*. Sci. Rep., doi:10.1038/srep34438
- Mudd, S. M., Harel, M.-A., Hurst, M. D., **Grieve, S.W.D.**, and Marrero, S. M., *The CAIRN method: Automated, reproducible calculation of catchment-averaged denudation rates from cosmogenic radionuclide concentrations*, Earth Surf. Dynam., doi:10.5194/esurf-4-655-2016
- Clubb, F.J., Mudd. S.M., Attal, M., Milodowski, D.T., and **Grieve, S.W.D.**, *The relationship between drainage density, erosion rate, and hilltop curvature: implications for sediment transport processes*, J. Geophys. Res. Earth Surf., doi:10.1002/2015JF003747

Mudd, S.M., Attal, M., Milodowski, D.T., **Grieve, S.W.D.**, Valters, D.A., *A statistical framework to quantify spatial variation in channel gradients using the integral method of channel profile analysis.* J. Geophys. Res. Earth Surf., doi:10.1002/2013JF002981

### **Conference Presentations**

#### INVITED TALKS

- Grieve, S.W.D., *Uncovering signatures of geomorphic process through high resolution topography.* Presented at The Hutton Club, University of Edinburgh.
- Grieve, S.W.D., Reproducible geographic analysis: Insights from geomorphology. Presented at GIS Update, Edinburgh.

#### **ORAL PRESENTATIONS**

- Mudd, S.M., Sinclair, H.D., LeDivellec, T., Dallas, K., **Grieve, S.W.D.**, A single event in the Ladakh Himalaya resulted in erosion equivalent to grater than 1000 years of the average erosion rate. Presented at the BSG Annual General Meeting, Plymouth.
- Grieve, S.W.D., Mudd, S.M., Hurst, M.D., *Constraining hillslope sediment flux using high resolution topographic data*. Presented at the BSG Annual General Meeting, Southampton.
- Clubb, F.J., Mudd, S.M., Attal, M., Milodowski, D.T., **Grieve, S.W.D.**, *The Relationship between Drainage Density, Erosion Rate, and Hilltop Curvature: Implications for Sediment Transport Processes*. Presented at the BSG Annual General Meeting, Southampton.

#### POSTER PRESENTATIONS

- Hales, T.C., Parker, R.N., Mudd, S.M., **Grieve, S.W.D.**, *How do Colluvial Hollows Fill?* Presented at the AGU Fall Meeting, San Francisco.
- Hurst, M.D., **Grieve, S.W.D.**, Mudd, S.M., *Coupled analysis of hillslope and channel metrics for erosion rates in a tectonically active landscape.* Presented at the AGU Fall Meeting, San Francisco.
- Grieve, S.W.D., Mudd, S.M., Milodowski, D.T., Clubb, F.J., Furbish, D.J., *How does the resolution of topographic data impact the measurement of geomorphic processes?* Presented at the BSG Annual General Meeting, Plymouth.
- Mudd, S.M., Hurst, M.D., **Grieve, S.W.D.**, Milodowski, D.T., Clubb, F.J., Attal, M. *Detecting geomorphic processes and change with high resolution topographic data.* Presented at the EGU General Assembly, Vienna.
- Mudd, S.M., **Grieve, S.W.D.**, Milodowski, D.T., Hurst, M.D., Clubb, F.J., Valters, D.A., *LSD-TopoToolBox: Open source geomorphology.* Presented at the BSG Annual General Meeting, Southampton.
- Clubb, F.J., Mudd, S.M., Attal, M., Milodowski, D.T., **Grieve, S.W.D.**, *The Relationship between Drainage Density, Erosion Rate, and Hilltop Curvature: Implications for Sediment Transport Processes.* Presented at the AGU Fall Meeting, San Francisco.
- Parker, R.N., Hales, T.C., Mudd, S.M., **Grieve, S.W.D.**, *Precipitation and soil accumulation history modifies future landslide hazard.* Presented at the AGU Fall Meeting, San Francisco.

2015 Parker, R.N., Hales, T.C., Mudd, S.M., Grieve, S.W.D., Climate change has limited impact on soil-mantled landsliding. Presented at the EGU General Assembly, Vienna. Grieve, S.W.D., Mudd, S.M., Hales, T.C., How long is a hillslope? Presented at the AGU Fall 2014 Meeting, San Francisco. 2014 Mudd, S.M., Attal, M., Milodowski, D.T., Grieve, S.W.D., Valters, D.A., A statistical technique for identifying channels of different steepness in transient landscapes. Presented at the EGU General Assembly, Vienna. Classroom Teaching Experience (Course Level) Quantitative Methods in Earth Sciences, Laboratory Demonstrator (3rd year) 2016 Geomorphology, Laboratory Demonstrator and Tutor (2nd year) 2015 Object Oriented Software Engineering Principles, Laboratory Demonstrator (M.Sc.) 2014-2015 Object Orientated Software Engineering: Spatial Algorithms, Laboratory Demonstrator (M.Sc.) 2014-2015 Principles of Geographical Information Science, Laboratory Demonstrator (M.Sc.) 2014-2015 Introduction To Spatial Analysis, Laboratory Demonstrator (M.Sc.) 2014-2015 2014-2015 Distributed GIS, Laboratory Demonstrator (M.Sc.) Spatial Modelling, Laboratory Demonstrator (M.Sc.) 2014-2015 Earth Surface Systems Course Assistant (1st year) 2014 Fundamental Methods in Geography, Laboratory and Field Demonstrator (2nd year) 2014 Geo-Visualisation, Laboratory Demonstrator (M.Sc.) 2013-2016 Advanced Spatial Database Methods, Laboratory Demonstrator (M.Sc.) 2013-2015 Further Spatial Analysis, Laboratory Demonstrator (M.Sc.) 2013-2015 2013-2014 Earth Surface Systems, Laboratory Demonstrator and Tutor (1st year) Field Teaching Experience (Course Level) Cyprus field course (4th year honours) 2014-2015 Fundamental Field Methods in Geography (2nd year) 2014 Service 2017-**Reviewer**: Earth Surface Dynamics **Reviewer**: Entropy 2016-Reviewer: Earth Surface Processes and Landforms. 2016-Currency Reviewer: Reference Module in Earth Systems and Environmental Sciences, Else-2015 vier. **Session Chair** M.Sc. GIS postgraduate conference, University of Edinburgh. 2014-2015

# **Funding Received**

2014 British Society for Geomorphology Student Travel Grant

Award: £750

2014

NERC Cosmogenic Isotope Analysis Facility: *Hillslope-channel coupling in a steady-state land-scape*.

P.I.: Tristam Hales (Cardiff University)

Co. I. Simon M. Mudd, Robert Parker (Cardiff University) and Stuart W. D. Grieve.

Award: £19,320

Safe Software Grant Program

Award: Software licence for FME Desktop Edition

2011 SAAS Postgraduate Students' Allowances Scheme

Award: £3400

University of Edinburgh Postgraduate Bursary

Award: £1300

2011

# **Professional Memberships**

2014– American Geophysical Union

2014– British Society for Geomorphology